Guide to the Alice Brown Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Alice Brown papers
1890-1948
YCAL MSS 550
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.3
(6 boxes)
The Alice Brown Papers consist of drafts, correspondence, and printed material documenting the work of American poet, novelist, and dramatist, Alice Brown. The papers, which provide evidence of Brown's writing career and literary circle, are a window into the creative life of a New England woman writer at the turn of the twentieth century. Brown's correspondence with author Esther Willard Bates is of particular interest. Dating over a ten year period (1938-1948) the letters consist of Brown's correspondence to Bates and contain her reflections on literature, mutual friends, and general observations on her writing and life.
Brown, Alice, 1857-1948
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Alice Brown, 1949. Other material came to the library in small quantities from various sources as indicated on individual folders.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Alice Brown (1857-1948)
Alice Brown, American poet, novelist, and dramatist, was born in Hampton Falls, New Hampshire, on December 5, 1857 to Levi Brown and Elizabeth Lucas. She attended Robinson Seminary in Exeter from which she graduated in 1876. After teaching for a brief period in New Hampshire, Brown moved to Boston in 1880 where she taught and worked for the Christian Register and the Youth's Companion (which she joined in 1885), before leaving teaching to write full time.
During her writing career Brown published novels, short stories, plays, and poetry. Her novels include Stratford-by-the-Sea (1884), Fools of Nature (1887), King's End (1901), Margaret Warrener (1901), The Day of His Youth (1897), and Kingdom in the Sky (1932). Many of Brown's short stories and verse were published in magazines, however, some of her short stories were collected in Meadow-Grass: Tales of New England Life (1895), Tiverton Tales (1899), High Noon (1904), The County Road (1906) and Country Neighbors (1910). Brown's poetry collections include The Road to Castaly (1896) and Ellen Prior (1923). Brown also authored biographies of Mercy Otis Warren (1896) and Louise Guiney (1921). In 1913 Brown won the Winthrop Ames prize for her play Children of Earth: A Play of New England, which Ames produced at the Booth Theater on Broadway and at the Schubert Theatre in New Haven, Connecticut in 1915.
Brown worked collaboratively with other authors, such as Louise Imogen Guiney and Harriet Prescott Spofford, with whom she coauthored Three Heroines of New England Romance. Brown and Guiney also jointly published a biographical study of Robert Louis Stevenson (1895). In 1907 Brown was one of twelve authors who contributed to The Whole Family: A Novel by Twelve Authors, which first appeared as a serial in Harper's Bazaar. In addition to these collaborations Brown was also involved with the Boston Authors Club (she served as president from 1920 to 1922).
Brown died in Boston, Massachusetts, on June 21, 1948.
Scope and Contents
The Alice Brown Papers consist of writings, correspondence, and printed material documenting the work of American poet, novelist, and dramatist, Alice Brown. The papers, which provide evidence of Brown's writing career and literary circle, are a window into the creative life of a New England woman writer at the turn of the twentieth century.
Brown's manuscripts provide insight into her creative process. In some cases Brown's writing projects can be traced from her initial handwritten drafts to the final published version (some of her drafts, and even printed versions, contain corrections). The Writings series largely consists of Brown's verse and short stories published in magazines such as Harper's Bazaar and Woman's Home Companion. A selection of Brown's other works, such as Children of Earth: A Play of New England, are also included in the Writings series. The Printed Material series includes publications by Brown as well as articles and promotional material about Brown. As the papers illustrate, Brown reflected on the literature she was reading, as can be found in her notes and jottings in blank pages of The Flying Teuton.
Brown's correspondence can be found in both the Writings and Correspondence series and reflects her personal and professional relationships. Brown's correspondence with author Esther Willard Bates is of particular interest. Dating over a ten year period (1938-1948) the letters consist of Brown's correspondence to Bates and contain her reflections on literature, mutual friends, and general observations on her writing and life.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Writings, 1890-1945. II. Correspondence, 1938-1948. III. Printed Material, 1896-1945.
American literature -- 19th century; American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 19th century -- Archives; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Women authors, American; Bates, Esther Willard, 1884-; Brown, Alice, 1857-1948
- Writings, 1890-1945; Series I; 2.09; (5 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
  Scope and Contents
  The series consists of drafts and printed versions of a number of Brown's writings, including poetry, short stories, and plays. The series also includes some correspondence, largely reflecting Brown's professional relationships.
  - "Adoration of the Dying," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Adventure," printed version, Harper's, 1926 June (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "The Advisory Board," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Age and His Beating Heart," typescript, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Alien Stairs," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "And Yet a Miracle," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Angie," typescripts, undated (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - "Anonymous Benefactions," printed version, Harper's, 1919 August (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "As the Law Directs," printed version, Harper's, 1923 March (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "Autumnal Days," holograph and proofs, December 7 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Before the Flood," typescript, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "The Begging Bowl," holograph, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - "Biography at Large," printed version, The Writer, 1932 January (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "The Body Speaks," holograph and typescript, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - "The Captives," typescript and printed version, McCall's Magazine, 1920 May (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Charles Lamb: A Play, holograph and typescripts, undated (Box 1, Folder 17-19)
  - Children of Earth: A Play of New England, typescripts, undated (Box 2, Folder 20-22)
  - "Commander Bear," holograph and typescript, corrected, undated (Box 2, Folder 23-24)
  - "The Common Cup," typescript, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - "Creation," typescript, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - "Dear Gaffer Death," holograph and typescript, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - "Death," typescript, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - "The Defeated," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - "The Dialect Story," typescript, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - "A Discord Stilled," printed version, Harper's Bazaar, 1916 December 13 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - "Don't Be Too Sorry," holograph, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - "The Dream," typescripts, corrected, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - "The Ears of the Deaf," printed version, Harper's, 1923 January (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - "Earth to Earth," typescript, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - "Elisabeth," holograph, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - "The Evening and the Morning," printed version, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - "Exiled To Earth," typescript, undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - "Faith," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - "Florida Lee," typescript and printed version, Harper's Bazaar, 1912 December (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - The Flying Teuton, printed version, dummy with only the title page and the first page of text, largely consists of blank pages on which Brown recorded a reading list, 1918-1945 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Foreward to the poetry of Harriet Elizabeth Prescott Spoffard, typescript, undated (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - "Forfeits," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - "The Garden of the Birds," typescript, undated (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - "The Girl in the Tree," printed version, Harper's, 1924 August (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - "Golden Manitou," typescript and printed version, Women's Home Companion, 1913 September (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - "The Golden Wedding," printed version, Women's Home Companion, 1908 September (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - "The Grass-Green Maid," typescript, printed version, and correspondence, circa 1905 (Box 3, Folder 48-49)
  - "Hayfields and the Walls of Troy," typescript, undated (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - "Heart of Stone," holograph and typescript, undated (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - "Heavens and Earth," typescript, undated (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - "The House with the Tower," Harper's, 1914 May (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - "The Hurrying Man," typescript, undated (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - "Ice Carts of the Mind," typescript, undated (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - "The Imagination of Man," holograph and typescript, undated (Box 3, Folder 56-57)
  - "In March," holograph, undated (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - "In October," holograph and page proof, 1945 October 16 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - "Invitation," holograph, undated (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - "A Judgement from Above," printed version, Harper's, 1921 June (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - "The Kingdom of the Child," typescript, undated (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - "Leaf Lineage from the Sun," holograph, undated (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - "A Lion in the Way," printed version, Harper's Bazaar, 1900 June (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - "The Little Elm," typescript and printed version, Ladies Home Journal, 1921 August (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - "Little Windows into the World," typescripts and printed version, undated (Box 3, Folder 66-68)
  - "The Littlest Bell," printed version, Harper's Bazaar, 1916 December 11 (Box 4, Folder 69)
  - "Long Love and Memory," typescripts, undated (Box 4, Folder 70)
  - "Louise Imogen Guiney," typescript, 1920 (Box 4, Folder 71)
  - "Love," typescripts, undated (Box 4, Folder 72)
  - "The Maid and Her Body," holograph and typescripts, undated (Box 4, Folder 73)
  - "A Man and His Mind," typescript, undated (Box 4, Folder 74)
  - "The Man and His Rose-Garden," printed version, corrected, Harper's, 1906 December (Box 4, Folder 75)
  - "The Man Who Wanted to Be Safe," printed version, Harper's, 1907 (Box 4, Folder 76)
  - "The Man Who Was Obstinate," printed version, 1906 December (Box 4, Folder 77)
  - "A March Wind," typescript, 1931 February 17 (Box 4, Folder 78)
  - "The Medicine Man," printed version, undated (Box 4, Folder 79)
  - "A Mind-Cure," typescripts and published version, Harper's, 1914 August (Box 4, Folder 80)
  - "A Minister of Grace," printed version, undated (Box 4, Folder 81)
  - "Mnemosyne," typescript, undated (Box 4, Folder 82)
  - "The Mother," typescript, undated (Box 4, Folder 83)
  - "The Mother and Her Son," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 4, Folder 84)
  - "The Mourning Veil," printed version, undated (Box 4, Folder 85)
  - "My Lady's Ring," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 4, Folder 86)
  - "Next Year's Garden," typescript and printed version, Good Housekeeping, undated (Box 4, Folder 87)
  - "Nicholas Woodman," typescript and printed version, Harper's, 1916 October (Box 4, Folder 88)
  - "Night and World War," holograph, undated (Box 4, Folder 89)
  - "Northern Lights," typescript, undated (Box 4, Folder 90)
  - "The Offering," typescript, undated (Box 4, Folder 91)
  - "Old Age," printed version, undated (Box 4, Folder 92)
  - "An Old Debt," typescript and printed version, Woman's Home Companion, 1917 November (Box 4, Folder 93)
  - "Old Lemuel's Journey," printed version, corrected, undated (Box 4, Folder 94)
  - "Pluto's Baggage," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 4, Folder 95-96)
  - "The Poet Who Lost His Pen," typescript, undated (Box 4, Folder 97)
  - "The Prince's Ball," printed version, Harper's, 1916 February (Box 4, Folder 98)
  - "Psyche," printed version, Harper's, 1919 July (Box 4, Folder 99)
  - "The Rescue," holograph, circa 1930 (Box 4, Folder 100)
  - "Saint Valina Speaks," holograph, undated (Box 5, Folder 101)
  - "The Rose Tree," typescript, undated (Box 5, Folder 102)
  - "Sainthood," holograph and typescript, undated (Box 5, Folder 103)
  - "Seven Seas," holograph, undated (Box 5, Folder 104)
  - "The Shadow," typescripts, undated (Box 5, Folder 105)
  - "Shelley's Birthday," typescript, undated (Box 5, Folder 106)
  - "Shooting Stars," printed version, Woman's Home Companion, 1920 November (Box 5, Folder 107)
  - "A Sinner Saved," printed version, Harper's Bazaar, 1916 December (Box 5, Folder 108)
  - Sonnets, untitled, typescript and holograph, undated (Box 5, Folder 109)
  - "The Sower," printed version, Outlook, 1907 May 25 (Box 5, Folder 110)
  - "The Spinners," typescript, undated (Box 5, Folder 111)
  - "The Spring of the Year," typescript and printed version, Delineator, 1913 April (Box 5, Folder 112)
  - "The Creature Named I," typescript and printed version, undated (Box 5, Folder 113)
  - "Three Bachelor Birds," printed version, undated (Box 5, Folder 114)
  - "Three Men," typescript, undated (Box 5, Folder 115)
  - "Thrush Song," holograph and typescript, undated (Box 5, Folder 116)
  - "Time's Revenges," printed version, Pictorial Review, 1916 April (Box 5, Folder 117)
  - "Timothy Cole," typescript, undated (Box 5, Folder 118)
  - "To a Painted Bride," typescript, undated (Box 5, Folder 119)
  - "A Tomb Unsealed," printed version, 1914 May (Box 5, Folder 120)
  - "The Traveling Larkspur," typescript and printed version, Woman's Home Companion, 1913 April (Box 5, Folder 121)
  - "The Unknown Beloved," printed version, undated (Box 5, Folder 122)
  - "An Unowned Legacy," typescript and printed version, Saturday Evening Post, 1899 December (Box 5, Folder 123)
  - Untitled short story, undated (Box 5, Folder 124)
  - "Vestigia," holograph and typescript, undated (Box 5, Folder 125)
  - "The Vision," typescript, undated (Box 5, Folder 126)
  - "The Visitant," typescript, undated (Box 5, Folder 127)
  - "Wedding-Gifts," typescript and printed version, Harper's, 1915 November (Box 5, Folder 128)
  - "The Window and the Tree," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 5, Folder 129)
  - "The Witch Wife," typescript, undated (Box 5, Folder 130)
  - "The Woman Whom God Loved," printed version, corrected, Outlook, 1906 (Box 5, Folder 131)
  - Various untitled manuscripts, holograph and typescript and correspondence, 1890-1912, undated (Box 5, Folder 132)
  - Notes on books read by Brown, typescript, undated (Box 5, Folder 133)
- Correspondence, 1938-1948; Series II; 10
  Arranged chronologically.
  The series is largely comprised of Brown's outgoing letters to author Esther Willard Bates.
  - Bates, Esther Willard, 1938-1948, undated (Box 5, Folder 134-140)
  - Various correspondents, 1940, undated (Box 5, Folder 141-143)
- Printed Material, 1896-1945; Series III; 0.21; (1 box)
  Arranged alphabetically.
  The series contains newspaper clippings, publicity, and theatre programs by and about Brown.
  - Alice Brown (New York: MacMillan Company) and "Books by Alice Brown" (Houghton, Mifflin and Company), 1923-1927 (Box 6, Folder 144)
  - "Children of Earth," theatre programs, 1915 (Box 6, Folder 145)
  - Clippings and page proofs, 1896-1945 (Box 6, Folder 146-148)